Guide to the Abraham Hayward Collection, 1234, November 2014
Yale University Library
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
General Collection of Modern Books and Manuscripts
Series Title Proper
Abraham Hayward collection 1791-1962 or something
GEN MSS 553
Hayward, A. (Abraham), 1801-1884.
Total Boxes: 7 (incl. 3 oversize boxes)
Linear Feet: 5.51'
Correspondence, printed materials, other papers, and photographs related to Abraham Hayward, as well as the research materials of Hayward biographer Brian Roberts. Outgoing correspondence includes letters to Hayward's sisters Fanny and Mary Anne Hayward, as well as publisher Richard Bentley. Incoming correspondence primarily consists of letters from members of Hayward's literary and political circles, including George Bentley; John Thaddeus Delane; Edward Everett; Alexander William Kinglake; John Murray; Henry Pelham, Duke of Newcastle; Viscountess Emily Lamb Palmerston; Horace Smith, and others. Topics discussed in Hayward's corresondence include contemporary politics; publishing concerns; London society; and invitations to dine. Third party correspondence consists of letters to Fanny Hayward. The bulk of the printed materials consists of pamphlets, a petition, and clippings related to a controversy over the Inner Temple's rules for election to the bench, which resulted from a dissenter rejecting Hayward. Printed materials also include title pages inscribed by and to Hayward; a theater program; calling cards; clippings; and a menu from the Café de Paris. Other papers include an account of the estate of Robert Abraham, for whom Hayward was the executor; Hayward's passport (1862-1871); a design for a fruit garden; and whist instructions. Photographs consist of 12 cartes-de-visite, including portraits of Abraham Hayward; Mrs. Cornwallis West; Mrs. Wheeler; Olive Campbell; Florence de Bretton; Madaillae Florian; and Countess Fanny Karolyi. Brian Roberts research materials consist of correspondence; typescripts for three chapters of an unfinished biography of Hayward; manuscript and typescript transcriptions of correspondence and writings related to Hayward; a biographical timeline; and other research papers.
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library P. O. Box 208240 New Haven, CT 06520-8240 Email: beinecke.library@yale.edu Phone: (203) 432-2972 Fax: (203) 432-4047
Administrative Information
Provenance
The Abraham Hayward Collection was acquired through purchase from Christopher Edwards on the George Henry Nettleton Fund, 2003.
Custodial History
paragraph
custodhist/acqinfo/head
custodhist/acqinfo/p
custodhist/acqinfo/acqinfo/head
custodhist/acqinfo/acqinfo/p
Alt Form
Alt Form paragraph
Accruals
Accruals paragraph
Appraisal
Appraisal paragraph
Fileplan
Fileplan paragraph
Originalsloc
Originalsloc paragraph
phystech
phystech paragraph
Separated Material
blah blah
Archref
Bibref
Extref Ref Title
Related Material
blah blah
Archref
Bibref
Extref Ref Title
Related Material
blah blah
Archref
Bibref
Extref Ref Title
Related Material
blah blah
Archref
Bibref
Extref Ref Title
Information about Access
This collection is open for research. Restricted Fragile Oversize in box 7 may only be consulted with permission of the appropriate curator. Preservation photocopies or photographic prints for reference use have been substituted in the main files.
Legal Status FOO BAR.
subhead
recursion recursion recursion
ABRAHAM HAYWARD (1801-1884)
Abraham Hayward, 1801-1884, was an English essayist and translator. Born in Wiltshire, Hayward studied at several schools, including Blundell's School in Tiverton, before moving to London and enrolling at the Inner Temple in 1824. He was called to the bar in 1832, but after the success of his 1833 translation of Goethe's Faust, the first translation of Faust into English, he pursued a career in journalism and literature. He never married.
Residing in London for the rest of his life, Hayward was well-connected in literary and political circles, counting among his acquaintances Thomas Babington Macaulay, William Makepeace Thackeray, W. E. Gladstone, and others. He contributed to many periodicals, including Quarterly Review, Monthly Magazine, and Edinburgh Review, and wrote several books, including collections of essays and biographies of Goethe and Mrs. Thrale (a friend of Dr. Johnson).
Hayward was involved in a controversy in 1845 over the Inner Temple's rules governing elections to the bench of the Inner Temple. Having received an appointment from Lord Chancellor Lyndhurst, Hayward then failed to win election to the bench. He attributed the rejection to a grudge held by a Mr. Roebuck who, according to Inner Temple tradition, was able to exclude him with a single black ball.
Description of the Papers
The Abraham Hayward Collection consists of correspondence, printed materials, phtographs, and other papers related to Abraham Hayward (1801-1884), a London essayist and translator, as well as the research papers of Brian Roberts, who started but abandoned a biography of Hayward in the 1950s. The papers, which span the years 1791-1962, are stored in seven boxes (including 3 oversize), and are organized into five series: Correspondence, Printed Materials, Other Papers, Photographs, and Brian Roberts Research Materials. The papers document Hayward's familial relations, the literary and political circles of mid-nineteeth century London, and a controversy involving Hayward and the Inner Temple.
Series I, Correspondence, is arranged alphabetically in three subseries: Outgoing, Incoming, and Third Party Correspondence. The bulk of the outgoing correspondence consists of letters to Hayward's two sisters, Fanny and Mary Anne Hayward. In his letters to his sisters, Hayward discusses his travels, London society, and politics, in particular the governments of Gladstone and Disraeli. Outgoing correspondence also includes letters from Hayward to the publisher Richard Bentley regarding articles and book reviews.
Incoming correspondence consists of letters to Hayward from George Bentley, John Thaddeus Delane, Edward Everett, Alexander William Kinglake, John Murray, Henry Pelham, Viscountess Emily Lamb Palmerston, and Horace Smith, and others. Topics include invitations to dine, the politics of Gladstone and Disraeli, Hayward's political appointments, and the publication of various articles, reviews, and pamphlets. The bulk of the third party correspondence is to Fanny Hayward a decade after Abraham Hayward's death.
Series II, Printed Materials, is arranged chronologically in two subseries: Inner Temple Affair and Other Printed Materials. Inner Temple Affair materials consist of two pamphlets, a petition, and clippings related to the controversy that arose from Hayward's failed election to the Inner Temple bench. Other printed materials include titlepages, a theater program, a menu from the Café de Paris, clippings, a circular on John Stuart Mill's antipopulation theory, and a broadside, "Men of the Day, No. 117, Mr. Abraham Hayward, Q.C."
Series III, Other Papers, is arranged chronologically and includes the following: an account of the estate of Robert Abraham, for whom Abraham Hayward was an executor; Abraham Hayward's passport for the years 1862-1871; a copy of his entry in Blundell's School registry; an undated design for a fruit garden or orchard; manuscript copies of poems by Caroline Sheridan Norton, Rev. E.D. Rhodes, and others; and whist instructions.
Series IV, Photographs, consists of a carte-de-visite album containing 12 cartes-de-visite of Abraham Hayward and eleven women, including Mrs. Cornwallis West, Mrs. Wheeler, Olive Campbell, Florence de Bretton, Madaillae Florian, and Countess Fanny Karolyi.
Series V, Brian Roberts Research Materials, is arranged in four subseries: Correspondence, Writings, Notes, and Other Papers. Correspondence is arranged alphabetically and includes letters from many people Roberts contacted in the course of his research on Abraham Hayward, including members of the Hayward family and Muriel Abbot-Anderson, who helped Roberts with local research in England's West Country. Writings include typescript drafts of chapters 1, 2, and 3 of Roberts's biography of Hayward.
The bulk of Brian Roberts's research notes consists of manscript transcriptions of correspondence and writings related to Hayward. The manuscript transcriptions are arranged approximately by the decade of the original document. Roberts's notes also include typescript transcriptions, a biographical timeline, a research notebook containing transcriptions of letters present in Series I, and note cards.
Oversize material is housed in boxes 5 and 6. Restricted Fragile Oversize material is stored in box 7 and contains oversize fragile originals for which preservation photocopies have been made for reference use and filed in the regular series run.
Access Terms
This collection is indexed under the following access points in Orbis, the Yale University Library online catalog.
Subjects
Name McNamerson; Boston (Massachusetts).; Watercolors; Rush family of
New /> Hampshire; Entertaining; Moby-Dick, or The Whale; Abraham, Robert, d. 1833 --Estate.; Bentley, George, 1828-1895.; Bentley, Richard, 1794-1871.; Delane, John Thaddeus, 1817-1879.; Everett, Edward, 1794-1865.; Hayward, A. (Abraham), 1801-1884.; Hayward, Fanny, d. 1904.; Hayward, Mary Anne.; Kinglake, Alexander William, 1809-1891.; Murray, John, 1808-1892.; Newcastle, Henry Pelham, Duke of, 1811-1864.; Palmerston, Emily Lamb, Viscountess, 1787-1869.; Roberts, Brian.; Smith, Horace, 1779-1849.; Inner Temple (London, England); Inner Temple (London, England) (Great Britain, Europe) (Earth, Solar System); Authors, English --19th century.; Gardens --Design --England.; Politics and culture --England --History --19th century.; Publishers and publishing --England --History --19th century.; Whist.; Cartes-de-visite.; Menus --France --Paris.; Passports.
Authors
Hayward, A. (Abraham), 1801-1884.; Roberts, Brian.
Occupations and Functions
Authors --England --19th century.
Collection Contents
paragraph
DSC ADDRESS
blockquote paragraph in dsc
DSC Note paragraph
DSC TABLE
- Correspondence, 1833-1896; Series I.; 0.21' (43 folders)
  Series I, Correspondence, is arranged into three subseries: Outgoing, Incoming, and Third Party Correspondence. Each is arranged alphabetically.
  - OUTGOING
    - Bentley, [Richard], 1873-83 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Boyes, ----, n.y. Nov 3 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Hayward, Fanny; Hayward, Mary Anne, 1854-82, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 3-7)
  - INCOMING
    - Bancroft, B., 1881 Dec 17 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Bentley, George, n.y. Oct 21 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Blessington, Marguerite, Countess of, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Brougham and Vaux, Henry Brougham, Baron (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Caldwell, Anita S., n.d. (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - [Cornwallis?], ----, 1867 Jun 6 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Delane, John Thaddeus, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Everett, Edward, 1844 Mar 2 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Froude, [James Anthony], n.y. Oct 12 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Harvey, A., n.d. (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Hawtrey, [Edward Craven], 1833 Dec 28 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Hayter, William Goodenough, Sir, n.y. Aug 19 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Kinglake, [Alexander William], 1853 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Lhwyd, Angharad, n.y. Sep 11 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Lowe, [Robert, Viscount Sherbrooke], 1857 Feb 6 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Lytton, [Rosina Bulwer Lytton, Baroness?], 1872 Aug 20 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Murray, John, 1863 May 4 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Newcastle, [Henry Pelham, Duke of], 1858 Nov 6 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Palmerston, [Emily Lamb, Viscountess], n.d. (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Peel, Emily, Lady, 1859 Feb 6 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Platt, Thomas Joshua, Sir, 1846 May 25 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Smith, Horace, 1840 Jan 22 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Stirling-Maxwell, William, Sir, 1868 Nov 8 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Wellesley, [Henry], 1861 Mar 7 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Unidentified, 1834-80 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - THIRD PARTY
    - De Limberg Hiram, S. J., to Fanny Hayward, 1894 Dec 22 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Eaton, Alfred E., to [Fanny] Hayward, 1896 Dec 18 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Escott, T. H. S. (Thomas Hay Sweet) to [Fanny Hayward], 1895 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Farmer, E., to [Fanny] Hayward, 1893 Aug 12 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Hayward, J., to Mr. Pearce, 1896 Mar 31 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Mills, Dudley, to Fanny Hayward, n.y. Mar 27 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Shearer, George, to Herman Merivale and Henry Davison, 1846 Jan
      See: Series II. Printed Materials, Petition, Box 1, folder 44
    - Unidentified niece to [Fanny] Hayward, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Unidentified to [L. Waldgren?], n.d. (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Printed Materials, 1791-1896; Series II.; 0.21' (11 folders)
  Series II, Printed Materials, is arranged into two subseries: Inner Temple Affair and Other Printed Materials. Each is arranged chronologically.
  - INNER TEMPLE AFFAIR
    - Pamphlet, "Remarks on the Mode of Electing Benchers at the Inner Temple," annotated, 1845 (Box 1, Folder 41)
      London: Owen Richards, Law Bookseller, 194 Fleet Street
    - Untitled pamphlet by Abraham Hayward concerning the Inner Temple Affair, 1845 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Clippings related to the Inner Temple Affair, [ca. 1845] (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Petition, "To The Benchers of the Honorable Society of the Inner Temple," signed, 1846 Jan (Box 1, Folder 44)
      Includes manuscript copy of George [Shearer?] to Herman Merivale and Henry Davison, Jan 31, 1846
  - OTHER PRINTED MATERIALS
    - Titlepage, Commentaries on the Laws of England, by Sir William Blackstone, signed "A. Hayward", 1791 (Box 1, Folder 45)
      London: Printed by A. Strahan and W. Woodfall, for T. Cadell, in the Strand
      Includes engraving of Blackstone
    - Titlepage, Discours de M. Thiers sur le Régime Commercial de la France, signed "Monsier Hayward" by M. Thiers, 1851 (Box 1, Folder 46)
      Paris: Paulin, Lheureux et cie, Éditeurs, Rue Richelieu, 60
    - Theater program, "87 Eaton Place", 1867 Jun 20 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Calling and invitation cards, 1873, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Clippings related to Hayward, 1863-[74] (Box 1, Folder 49-52)
    - Menu, "Café de Paris, Angilbert et Guerraz, Glaciers-Restauranteurs," signed "A. Hayward", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 53)
      Paris: De l'Imprimerie de Gondelier Moorisset, Rue Saint-Denis, no. 350, et passage du Caire, no. 110
    - Circular, "John Stuart Mill's Antipopulation Theory the result of paternal teaching...", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 54)
      The full title is "John Stuart Mill's Antipopulation theory the result of paternal teaching and an essential part of the philosophy of the school."
    - Broadside, "Men of the Day, No. 117, Mr. Abraham Hayward, Q.C.", n.d.
- Other Papers, 1833-1885; Series III.; 0.21' (1 box)
  Series III, Other Papers, is arranged chronologically.
  - Account of the estate of Robert Abraham, 1833-38
  - Walland and Son timber account, 1841 Jan 25 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Abraham Hayward passport, 1862-71 (Box 2, Folder 56)
    Includes endorsements from Turkey, Italy, Russia, France, and Germany
  - Blundell's School, Tiverton. Manuscript copy of Abraham Hayward's entry in the school registry, 1885 May 18 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Garden plan, "A Sketch or design for an orchard and Fruit Garden" (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Manuscript copies of poems, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 59)
    Includes poems by Caroline Sheridan Norton, Rev. E. D. Rhodes, and others
  - Manuscript whist instructions, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Note enclosing feathers, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 61)
- Photographs, 1875-1878; Series IV.; 0.21' (1 box)
  - Carte-de-visite album, 1875-78 (Box 3, Folder 62)
    Contains 12 carte-de-visite portraits, showing Abraham Hayward and eleven women, including Mrs. Cornwallis West, Mrs. Wheeler, Olive Campbell, Florence de Bretton, Madaillae Florian, and Countess Fanny Karolyi
- Brian Roberts Research Materials, 1943-1962; Series V.; 0.42' (1 box)
  Series V, Brian Roberts Research Materials, is arranged into four subseries: Correspondence, Writings, Notes, and Other Papers. Correspondence is arranged alphabetically. Manuscript notes are arranged roughly by the decade of the original materials.
  - CORRESPONDENCE
    - Abbot-Anderson, Muriel, 1958-59 (Box 4, Folder 63-64)
    - Beale, Colin, 1958 May (Box 4, Folder 65)
    - Blake, Humphrey, 1958 Oct 16 (Box 4, Folder 66)
    - Elliot, Inez R., 1959 Jan 7 (Box 4, Folder 67)
    - Hart, E. A. P., 1958 Aug 27 (Box 4, Folder 68)
    - Hayward, J. C., 1958 Jun 4 (Box 4, Folder 69)
    - Hayward, John, 1958-59 (Box 4, Folder 70)
    - Hayward, Margaret, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 71)
    - Hayward, Mary M., 1958 Oct (Box 4, Folder 72)
    - Holden, Bill, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 73)
    - Long, L. J., 1958 May 20 (Box 4, Folder 74)
    - Mahood, A. S., 1957 Nov 6 (Box 4, Folder 75)
    - Mineka, Francis E., 1958 Aug 19 (Box 4, Folder 76)
    - Moody, Graham C., 1958 (Box 4, Folder 77)
    - [Pauly?], C. F., 1958 Mar 26 (Box 4, Folder 78)
    - Pauly, Michael St. John, 1958 May 29 (Box 4, Folder 79)
    - Rathbone, Maurice G., 1958 Aug 29 (Box 4, Folder 80)
    - Roberts, T. V., 1961-62 (Box 4, Folder 81)
    - Sandell, Richard E., 1957 Dec 9 (Box 4, Folder 82)
    - Scott, Joseph W., 1958 May 19 (Box 4, Folder 83)
    - Steele, Edwin H., 1958 Dec 5 (Box 4, Folder 84)
    - Stuart, D. W., 1958 May 10 (Box 4, Folder 85)
    - Walker, E., 1958 Apr 17 (Box 4, Folder 86)
    - Wyck, ----, 1958 Feb 4 (Box 4, Folder 87)
    - ----, Donald, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 88)
    - Unidentified, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 89)
  - WRITINGS
    - Biography of Abraham Hayward
      - Typescript, "Chapter 1", n.d. (Box 4, Folder 90)
      - Typescript, "Chapter 2", n.d. (Box 4, Folder 91)
      - Typescript, "Chapter 2", n.d. (Box 4, Folder 92)
      - Typescript, "Chapter 3", n.d. (Box 4, Folder 93)
  - NOTES
    Manuscript transcriptions
    - Writings and correspondence related to Hayward (1820s-1950s, n.d.)
    - Typescript transcriptions of writings and correspondence related to Hayward (Box 4, Folder 94)
    - Hayward timeline notes (1834-72), n.d. (Box 4, Folder 95)
    - Research notebook, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 96)
      Includes manuscript transcriptions of letters in Series I, Correspondence
    - Note cards, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 97)
  - OTHER PAPERS
    - British Museum application for photography of Vanity Fair cartoons, 1943 Nov 13 (Box 4, Folder 98)
    - Invoice for purchase of "Hayward colln", 1959 Dec 15 (Box 4, Folder 99)
    - Prints of a portrait of Laura Bell, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 100)
- Oversize, 1.67' (1 box)
  - Broadside, "Men of the Day, No. 117, Mr. Abraham Hayward, Q.C." (in Series II), n.d. (Box 5, Folder 101)
  - Account of the estate of Robert Abraham (in Series III), 1833-38 (Box 5, Folder 102)
  - Writings and correspondence related to Hayward (1820s-30s) (in Series V) (Box 6, Folder 103)
  - Writings and correspondence related to Hayward (1840s) (in Series V) (Box 6, Folder 104-106)
  - Writings and correspondence related to Hayward (1850s) (in Series V) (Box 6, Folder 107)
  - Writings and correspondence related to Hayward (1860s) (in Series V) (Box 6, Folder 108)
  - Writings and correspondence related to Hayward (1870s) (in Series V) (Box 6, Folder 109-110)
  - Writings and correspondence related to Hayward (1880s) (in Series V) (Box 6, Folder 111)
  - Writings and correspondence related to Hayward (1890s) (in Series V) (Box 6, Folder 112)
  - Writings and correspondence related to Hayward (1900s-10s) (in Series V) (Box 6, Folder 113)
  - Writings and correspondence related to Hayward (1920s-50s) (in Series V) (Box 6, Folder 114)
  - Writings and correspondence related to Hayward (n.d.) (in Series V) (Box 6, Folder 115-116)
- Restricted Fragile Oversize, 1.67' (1 box)
  Box 7, Restricted Fragile Oversize, contains fragile originals. The material is arranged in folder order and may only be seen with the permission of the appropriate curator. Preservattion photocopies have been substituted in the main files for reference use.
  - Box 1, folder 49 (Box 7, Folder 117)
  - Box 1, folder 50 (Box 7, Folder 118)
  - Box 1, folder 51 (Box 7, Folder 119)
  - Box 1, folder 52 (Box 7, Folder 120)